Anders Ytterström

Frontend Engineer, Full Stack Developer, Web standardista

Herrhagsvägen 53, 791 76 Falun, Sweden

**** +46 70 216 96 45

💂 madr

🏦 madr.se

Skills

Programming languages HTML, CSS (Sass), Python, JavaScript (TypeScript),

Elixir, Rust, PHP

Development process CI/CD, Automated testing, Mentoring, Mob

programming, Pair programming

Web Backend Frameworks Django, Flask, Phoenix (LiveView), Express

Web Frontend React, Redux, Vue, Svelte, Lit, OOCSS, BEM, Living

styleguides

Build systems Webpack, Parcel, esbuild

Content management Wordpress, Joomla

Testing pytest, Jest, Lighthouse, Axe, VoiceOver, Voice

Assistant, NVDA, Cypress, WebDriverIO, Web Test

Runner

Deployment AWS, Docker (Podman), Kubernetes, Ansible,

Terraform, Azure DevOps

Services & Infrastructure Nameko, RabbitMQ, Celery, Kibana, Prometheus

Databases MySQL, Postgres, Elasticsearch, GraphQL, Influx,

Timescale

Version control Git, Subversion

Operating systems Linux, Mac OS, Windows

Other skills Inclusive communication, Accessibility compliance,

Technical writing

Languages Swedish (native), English (fluent)

Anders Ytterström, Web Developer with 16 years of passion. I strive to constantly come up with new ways of improving both products and processes for all participants in projects I am part of.

I prefer my coffee black, just like my metal, and preferably drip brewed by hand.

I also aim to be a roadie, not a rockstar, as well as defending boring tech.

Experience

Stratsys, Process management platform (SaaS)

SENIOR FRONTEND ARCHITECT

Remote position
Mar 2022–now

- Part of a team consisting of Frontend architects and UX designers.
- Responsible for the design system, frontend DX and Microfrontend toolchain and architecture.
- Writing Web components with full ARIA compability, according to the spec.
- QA and manual testing with screen readers (NVDA, VoiceOver).

Iteam, Technical Innovation agency

Remote position

FULL STACK DEVELOPER

Sep 2021-Mar 2022

- All source code are released by a FOSS license.
- Backend programming in Node.js, TypeScript, Express and Next.js.
- Frontend development in React, Jotai, Formik, Styleguidist and Figma.
- Code labs and skill sharing.

Kundo, Customer service company (SaaS)

Stockholm, Sweden

FULL STACK DEVELOPER

Mar 2017-Sep 2021

- T-shaped frontend developer focusing on WCAG 2.0 AA, design and mentoring.
- Roles besides development: Team Lead, Tech Lead and Security administrator (briefly).
- Backend programming in Django and Phoenix, with RabbitMQ as broker/RPC and Celery as job queue.

Adeprimo, Digital Fullservice agency

Östersund, Sweden

SYSTEMS DEVELOPER

Oct 2007-Feb 2017

- T-shaped Systems developer focusing on frontend and backend web development. Fields: Media, Destination, Tourism.
- High demand on customer experience and context switching.
- Distributed, remote-first teams with members located in Vaasa (Finland), Örebro (Sweden) and Östersund (Sweden).
- Consulting for startups based in Östersund and Åre, Sweden.
- Polopoly, Python, PHP, Sass, jQuery, Wordpress, SilverStripe, .NET.

Pierce, Ecommerce (Motocross, MC and Snowmobile accessories)

Åre, Sweden

WEB DEVELOPER

Mar–Jul 2015

- Development and maintainence for 24mx.se, XLMoto.se och sledstore.se.
- .NET, C#, Azure.

Västsvensk tidningsdistribution (VTD), Distribution

Alingsås, Sweden

NEWSPAPER CARRIER

Jul-Aug 2007

• Temporary summer position. Delivering Göteborgs-Posten to 300 households by foot. It rained every night.

Moment Marketing, Startup

Stockholm, Sweden

WEB DESIGNER

Sep 2006-Apr 2007

• Frontend development assistance. Employment by the hour.

Education

STUDENT DEGREE

Media and Communication Science, Mid Sweden University

Sundsvall, Sweden

DEGREE OF BACHELOR OF ARTS (INCOMPLETE)

2004-2007

Web design, Computer science, Computer engineering, Programming (Java, C)

Staffanskolan secondary school

Söderhamn, Sweden 2001–2004

Media programme, vocational, media production, graphical communication

Courses, Conferences & Certifications

- ElixirConf EU, Warshawa (2020, postponed due to the Coronavirus pandemic)
- Att leda utan att vara chef, Företagsakademin (2019)
- Modern React with Redux, Udemy (2017)
- Ethical Programming from Scratch, Udemy (2018)
- Android Developer Nanodegree, Udacity (2017)
- PyConf, Stockholm (2017)
- Nordic.JS, Stockholm (2014)
- TiConf, Amsterdam (2014)
- FFConf, Brighton (2012)
- DevSum, Stockholm (2012)
- Certificed Scrum Master Course, Crisp AB (2010)

Projects

Tree View widget

SENIOR FRONTEND ARCHITECT, STRATSYS

Summer 2022

- Implement a reusable Tree View widget as a Web component (Custom element with Shadow DOM).
- Data-driven state over DOM State.
- Deployed by the MicroFrontend concept and practices.
- Fully accessible, with keyboard navigation and mouse gestures, according to the ARIA Authoring Practices guide.
- E2E/Integration tests in a set of real, headless browsers.
- Atomic Design, Microfrontends, Custom Elements, Design Systems, Style Guides, Web Components, Lit, Vue.js, ARIA Authoring Practices guides (APG).

Slussen FastAPI data adapter, Sveriges Almännytta

FULL STACK DEVELOPER, ITEAM

Okt-Dec 2021

- Turn Allmännyttan FastAPI from blob XML to compact JSON.
- The adapter was used to create a POC to joyfully report a fault of an rental object.
- Design sprint together with the stake holders.
- All code was open sourced.
- TypeScript, FastAPI, Express, React, MIT.

SEO-friendly embed of knowledgebase

FULL STACK DEVELOPER, KUNDO

Mar 2020-Mar 2021

- Embedded a knowledgebase on any site using a simple embed snippet, whereas the knowledgebase is embedded using fetch().
- Navigation between guides and text search included, all crawlable by googlebot.
- SPA-compliance.
- TypeScript, Jest, Google Search Console.

Accessibility Statement

FULL STACK DEVELOPER, KUNDO

Sep-Dec 2019

- Compliance of the EU Directive on the Accessibility of Public Sector Websites.
- Axe, W3C validators, Lighthouse, manual accessibility testing.

Kubernetes migration

FULL STACK DEVELOPER, KUNDO

Jan 2019-Dec 2020

- Migrating an AWS production environment (several service-modules in different programming languages, message queues and micro services) to Kubernetes, along with all in-house DevOps tooling.
- Goals: keep one command deploys to production, keep Kibana logging, supervision of all services.
- Terraform, Ansible, Docker, Helm, Prometheus, Kubectl, Minikube.

Facebook Opengraph client

FULL STACK DEVELOPER, KUNDO

Sep 2017-Mar 2019

- Integrating customer support questions posted on Facebook Pages and Messenger into the Dashboard.
- Needed to be done asyncronously to not tamper with API credibility.
- Python, Django, MyPy, Protobuf, RabbitMQ, Phoenix Presence+Channels, React
 + Redux

Security & GDPR accountable

FULL STACK DEVELOPER, KUNDO

Sep 2017-Feb 2019

Personal Projects

Advent of code

Every December since 2016, I challenge myself (and sometimes other collegues) to solve AOC puzzles in a programming language of my choice.

Tajm.me

As a consultant, time tracking is a crucial part of every day work, and using bad time tracking software sucks. For 5 years, I scratched my own itch. Django, DRF and Web standards at its core. Several experimental client side solutions built with D3, React, Vue, Android, iOS and GTK+. (Archived, 2012–2017)

Baslyft, bärs & burgare

My first Progressive Web App, with support to work fully offline once installed on a device. It's a simple app for logging reps, sets and PB's in the gym, with some nice tools built-in: 1RM calculator and KG-LBS converter. Touch-oriented design patterns, React, Redux, localStorage, ServiceWorker and other nifty Web API:s. (On hold, Sep 2019–)

Brütal Legend

A site to track progress of owning vinyl copies os songs licensed in an epic video game. Occasionally used as a real-world example to teach TypeScript, React and Redux concepts to collegues. (On hold)

Utsökt

A simple bookmarking and read list service, with integration to RSS feeds, Pocket and Slack. Inspired by the old, more minimal version of Instapaper. Elixir, Phoenix LiveViews. (In progress)

Smed

A pluggable static site generator, inspired by Metalsmith. The goal is to replace my own sites in Metalsmith, and to learn Rust. (In progress)

- Accountable for several projects to fulfil the GDPR directive up to May 25th, 2018 and onwards.
- Accountable for security processes and planning for the technical platform.

Engcon pricelist

INTERFACE DEVELOPER, CONSULTANT

Nov 2016-Feb 2017

- Prototyp-driven development of a digital version of a printed pricelist, focusing on effiency and MVP.
- Vue, Django, Twitter Bootstrap

Wide Ideas

FULL STACK DEVELOPER, CONSULTANT

Aug 2011-Feb 2017

- Development of an idea management platform.
- Handled DevOps, automation of workflows, development of web interface, and backend programming.
- PHP, Pligg, Python, Flask, MongoDB, Elastic Search

Östersundstidningar redesign

INTERFACE DEVELOPER

Mar-May 2011

- Complete redesign of 3 sites with the same locked (and oldfashioned) HTML.
- An Object-oriented CSS architecture (OOCSS) was used to create a design system and KSS-powered styleguide utilizing Sass mixins.

Mktwebb

INTERFACE DEVELOPER

Oct 2007-Aug 2009

- Shared technical solution for a publication platform for 40 newspapers across Sweden, with Polopoly as CMS.
- Technological ownership and mentoring others to write JavaScript.
- All HTML and CSS written in collaboration with backend programmers, UX researchers and designers.